<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Three sermons vpon Marke, the ninth chapter, 22.23. verses Containing fifteene doctrines, the particulars whereof appeare in the next pages following. / By Robert Cleauer.</title>
            <author>Cleaver, Robert, 1561 or 2-ca. 1625.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1611</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 106 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18973</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5392</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118642</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853849</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853849</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19247</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18973)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19247)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1062:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Three sermons vpon Marke, the ninth chapter, 22.23. verses Containing fifteene doctrines, the particulars whereof appeare in the next pages following. / By Robert Cleauer.</title>
                  <author>Cleaver, Robert, 1561 or 2-ca. 1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 51, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T C[reede] for William Welbie, and are to be sold at his shop in Pauls Church-yard, at the signe of the Swan,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1611.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>This item also appears as part of STC (2nd ed.) 6945.6 at reel 1955:15.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Mark IX, 22-23 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19247:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19247:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THREE SERMONS VPON MARKE, THE NINTH CHAP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, 22. 23. verſes. CONTAINING fifteene Doctrines, the particulars whereof appeare in the next pages following.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Robert Cleauer.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Thomas Creede (McKerrow 339)</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>T C.</hi> for <hi>William Welbie,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, at the ſigne of the Swan. 1611.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_doctrines">
            <pb facs="tcp:19247:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19247:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> THE DOC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TRINES OF THE THREE Sermons vpon Marke, the 9. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. 22. 23. verſes.</head>
            <list>
               <head>SERMON I.</head>
               <item>
                  <label>DOCT. I.</label> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat Sathans malice is bent euen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our bodies.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>2</label> That Gods owne children with their faith haue ſome mixture of vnbeliefe.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>3</label> That loue makes men to beare others bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens as if they were their owne.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>SERMON II.</head>
               <item>
                  <label>DOCT. I.</label> WHere Chriſt helpes any one in mercy, he firſt helpes his heart.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>2</label> That no man hath faith at command.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>3</label> The faithfull are ſtrongeſt and happieſt.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:19247:3"/>
               <item>
                  <label>4</label> Faith and godly ſorrow may well goe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>5</label> Chriſtians muſt ſee and acknowledge their graces.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>6</label> Faith ſhewes men their corruptions, and mooues them to ſeeke helpe againſt them.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>SERMON III.</head>
               <item>
                  <label>DOCT. 1.</label> CHriſt doth all in due time.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>2</label> Enemies of Gods Children ſhalbe rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>3</label> Sathan is deſirous to bereaue vs of our ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and limbs.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>4</label> A word of Chriſts mouth is ſufficient to helpe vs out of all diſtreſſes.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>5</label> It is all one with Chriſt, to driue the diuell out, and to keepe him out.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>6</label> Sathan neuer ſeemes more maſterfull then when he is ouer-maſtered.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="collection">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19247:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <div n="1" type="sermon">
               <head>The firſt Sermon.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>MARKE. 9.</bibl>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>Verſe 22.</bibl> And oft times hee caſteth him into the fire, and into the water, to deſtroy him: but if thou canſt doe anie thing, helpe vs: and haue compaſſion vpon vs.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>23</bibl> And IESVS ſaid vnto him, if shou canſt belieue it, all things are poſſible to him that belieueth.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>24.</bibl> And ſtraight way the father of the childe, crying with teares, ſaide; Lord, I beleeue, helpe my vnbeliefe.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He occaſion of theſe words is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the beginning of this hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: which was this, that a certaine man had a childe poſſeſſed by the diuell, which had made him dumbe and deaffe, and that from his child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood; in ſo much that he could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſpeake nor heare in all his life: This man in the abſence of Chriſt, brought him to his Diſciples, hearing that they had diſpoſſeſſed others, and therefore hoping to finde the like ſucceſſe for himſelfe: But when they had made triall, they found themſelues vnable to caſt the diuell out of his childe: wherevpon their aduerſaries were readie to inſult and triumph o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them. In the meane ſeaſon our Sauiour commeth among them, readie to vndertake the cauſe of his poore
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19247:4"/> Diſciples againſt their enemies; the father of this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed childe doth forthwith haſten vnto him, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters into ſpeech with him: Now theſe wordes do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine part of that conference which paſſed betwixt them; wherein wee may note theſe three things:</p>
               <p>
                  <label>1</label> 1. Firſt the petition of the man, with the reaſon of it: he beſought our Sauiour if he could doe any thing, that hee would haue compaſſion on him and his ſonne, and miniſter comfort vnto him, by giuing deliuerance vnto his childe, from his miſerable eſtate wherein hee was: and to moue him vn to greater commiſeration, he relateth vnto him in what ſort Satan did tyrannize ouer him, <hi>caſting him oft times into the fire, to burne him, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the water to drowne him.</hi> Verſe 22.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>2</label> 2. Secondly, our Sauiours anſwere, where wee may obſerue, that as the man came with an [<hi>If</hi>] ſaying, <hi>If thou canſt doe anie thing:</hi> ſo hee anſwereth him with the like; <hi>If thou canſt belieue this:</hi> that is, if thou canſt bee perſwaded of my power, that I am able to doe this, thy ſonne ſhall be helped (for that muſt needs be ſupplyed) and hee yeeldeth a reaſon thereof, <hi>all things are poſſible to the belieuer,</hi> verſ. 23: and therefore this is is not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible: as if Chriſt Ieſus ſhould haue ſaide; Whereas thou makeſt queſtion whether I can diſpoſſeſſe thy ſonne or not, know this, that if there be any doubt, it is on thy part, not on mine: if thou canſt belieue, thou ſhalt finde, that neither this, nor any other matter is too difficult for mee: this our Sauiour ſpeakes, for the hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of his weake faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>3</label> Thirdly, wee may note the replie of this man vpon Chriſt his ſpeech; hee <hi>crying with teares,</hi> ſaid, <hi>Lord I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue, helpe mine vnbeliefe:</hi> verſ. 24. Where we ſee that he acknowledgeth the grace of God, that hee did belieue in part: and withall, his owne weakeneſſe, that hee was troubled with vnbeliefe: againſt which, hee deſireth
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19247:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> Chriſt to <hi>helpe him;</hi> that is, to cure him of it, to giue him ſtrength againſt it, and deliuerance from it. And thus much for the order and ſenſe of the wordes; verſe 22. <hi>And oft times hee caſteth him into the fire, and into the water to deſtroy him:</hi>] whence obſerue this doctrine, that</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> 1. Satans malice is bent euen againſt mens bodies.</note> Satan is not onely an enemie vnto the ſoules of men, but alſo vnto their bodies.</p>
               <p>Hee doth not onely ſeeke their deſtruction ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie by drawing Gods wrath vpon them: but alſo cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally, by bringing afflictions &amp; miſeries vpon them; as here wee may ſee by his cruell dealing towards this child: albeit he had gotten an habitation in him, which was a thing wherein hee much delighted <note place="margin">Mark. 5. 8.</note> (as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by this, that hee counted it a torment to be caſt out, where once he had taken poſſeſſion;) yet hee vſed great violence towards him, caſting him into the fire, and into the water, being content to relinquiſh and loſe his holde, ſo that the childe might be deſtroyed. <note place="margin">Mark. 5. 5.</note> The like wee may reade in this ſame Euangeliſt, in his firſt chapter, where mention is made of one poſſeſſed, whom the diuell cauſed to flie from, and to eſchew the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of men, and to liue in the mountaines, and in the graues, and to knocke himſelfe with ſtones, and ſo to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe that ſtrength which he had giuen him, to his owne great hurt and torment. So alſo in his dealing with <hi>Iob,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iob. 1.</note> and with his children and ſeruants, we may obſerue how willing hee is to take libertie to hurt mens bodies, when it pleaſeth the Lord to graunt it vnto him.</p>
               <p>And for the further confirmation of this point,</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſon 1.</note> Let vs firſt take experience for one reaſon, to conuince vs of the truth hereof, and that in the limmes of Satan, who being led by his ſpirit, doe plainly manifeſt of what diſpoſition their maiſter is: now concerning them, it is ſaid, that <hi>the workes of their father they will doe;</hi> and of Satan, it is ſaid, <note place="margin">Iohn. 8. 44.</note> that <hi>he was a murtherer from the beginning:</hi>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:19247:5"/> whence it may be concluded, that the more diuelliſh men are, the more murderous and bloudie mindes they carrie: and therefore when the diuell was entered into <hi>Iudas,</hi> he preſently fell to practiſing againſt his maiſter: <note place="margin">1. Iohn. 3. 12.</note> and <hi>Caine</hi> being <hi>of that euill one, ſlue his brother:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 18. 10. 11.</note> and when the euill ſpirit came vpon <hi>Saule,</hi> he laid about him with his ſpeare, with full purpoſe to haue bereſt <hi>Dauid</hi> of his life: and ſo it is with ſwaggerers and drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards, and ſuch like helliſh perſons, when they haue no enemies to fall out with, they drawe their weapons on their friends, and many times murder their owne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions: which is an euident demonſtration of the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell affection that is in Sathans members, euen towards the bodies of men.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">2</note> Againe, this may be another reaſon of the point, that Sathan carrieth a deadly malice againſt all the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <note place="margin">Mark. 5.</note> (as we may ſee in his deſire to enter into the ſwine) and therefore much more vnto mankind: and that not onely againſt the Image of God renewed by the ſpirit of Chriſt, but euen againſt thoſe remnants thereof that are remaining in the nature of man: whence it is, that he is ſo violent againſt their bodies, and ſeekes to torture them as well as their ſoules, as carrying ſome ſtampe and impreſſion of Gods workemanſhip in them.</p>
               <p>This point ſerueth,</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Vſe.</note> Firſt for the iuſt reproofe and condemnation of their follie and madneſſe, that will vpon any occaſion haue recourſe vnto Sathan, or to any meanes of his inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, either for the relieuing of their eſtate, or the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of their bodies, or the helping of their children, or the like: howſoeuer ſuch doe in word profeſſe that they eſteeme of the diuell as of an vtter enemie vnto mankinde, yet indeed they ſhew the quite contrarie, <hi>viz.</hi> that they rather iudge him to be a friend, than a foe: for they will runne from God, and from their dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19247:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> friends, to ſeeke vnto him; and preferre his ſeruice before the ſeruice of any whoſoeuer he be. Many will ſerue the Lord hollowly, and their maiſters vntruſtily, but the diuell in good earneſt, and without hypocriſie, wholy applying themſelues to fulfill the luſts of the fleſh, they imagine that there is too much rigour in Gods lawe, and too much ſeueritie in mens dealings, and that Sathan is the beſt and kindeſt maiſter of all others: he will giue them full libertie to breake the Sabbath; to be drunken, to be wanton and laſciuious, to filſh and ſteale, and to doe any thing elſe whereunto their ſinfull nature leadeth them: they may haue any indulgence at his hands, without checke, or controule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and hence it commeth to paſſe that he hath ſuch troupes of followers, and that almoſt all the world are his ſeruants and vaſſals. But theſe men doe little conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in the meane while, what a cruell tyrant, and mortall aduerſarie he is vnto them, yea euen to their bodies.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Obiect.</note> How can that be (will ſome ſay) ſeeing that ſuch doe liue merily, and enrich themſelues in the world, and come to places of great preferment? If to take the cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes before named be to ſerue the diuel, ſurely (for ought we can ſee) he ſeemes to be a kinder maiſter than he is taken for.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſwer. 5</note> Nay, he is a cruell tyrant notwithſtanding all this, and that to the very outward man, for (that we may giue inſtance in ſome particulars) when Sathan giues libertie to any one to take his ſwing in ſwilling and drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king; doth he not by that meanes ouerthrow his eſtate, craze his braine, blemiſh his name, and fill his body full of noy ſome diſeaſes? and doth not the diuell then take a ſcourge as it were into his hand, wherewith he payeth them home that are giuen ouer to that inordinate courſe of life? So when he giues allowance vnto men to follow their couetous humour, doe they not pinch
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19247:6"/> their bellies, and depriue themſelues o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t times of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie foode? doe they not reſtraine their eyes from ſleepe in the night, and vexe themſelues with many painefull cares, as what if ſuch a cheſt ſhould be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken open? what if theeues ſhould get into ſuch a cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber? what if my ſeruants ſhould be vnfaithfull at home? What if they ſhould not looke well to my cattle abroad? with a thouſand ſuch troubleſome thoughts, which doe breake off their reſt, and impaire their hearts, and by degrees drawe dangerous diſeaſes vpon them: it would be too much to particularize in pleaſures of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers kinds, in gaming, in ambition, &amp; ſuch like: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in when the diuell hath once intangled men, he doth keepe them as it were in Bridewell. But grant for the time, that he is kinde vnto ſinfull perſons in letting them haue their fill of iniquitie, yet he is withall craftie, and ſeeketh to ouer-reach them by ſubtiltie: for he knoweth that his power is limited, ſo that he cannot doe what he would; and therefore he laboureth by drawing men vnto ſuch courſes as are diſpleaſing vnto the Lord, to put them ouer into his hand, (who as he well knowes) both can and will plague and puniſh them, either in body, or in ſoule, or in both: ſo that by preſenting before their eyes the benefits that they ſhall reape by ſinne, he doth but offer vnto them a ſugred cuppe, which hath deadly poyſon in the bottome of it: or a goodly faire baite, which hath a dangerous hooke in the midſts of it. His dealing herein, may not vnfitly be compared vnto the counſell which that falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Balaam</hi> gaue vnto <hi>Balac,</hi> king of <hi>Moab:</hi> who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he could not preuaile againſt the Iſraelites, ſo long as they continued in Gods fauour, but though hee curſed them, yet the Lord would bleſſe them: <note place="margin">Numb. 24. Reuel. 2. 14.</note> hee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſeth that King (if euer hee meant to doe them a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe) to vſe them kindly, and friendlie; to bidde them
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19247:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> to their wake, when they offered ſacrifice to their filthie Idoll, and there to make them good cheere, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, to offer vnto them ſome of their faireſt women; that ſo beeing drawen to ſinne againſt God, hee might exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute ſome iudgement vpon them: and this diuelliſh counſell was that indeed, which cauſed Gods people to taſte of his indignation. In the ſame manner doth Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan beguile the ſonnes of men: hee cannot bring vpon them that miſerie and miſchiefe that hee deſireth, and therefore hee ſtirreth men vp to prouoke the Lord by their pride, and voluptuouſnes, and worldlines, or ſome ſuch like corruptions, and then hauing made warre be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Lord and them, hee ſtands by and clappes his hands, to ſee him ſmiting and plaguing them for their offences.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Vſe. 2.</note> Secondly, conſidering that Satan is ſuch a cruell ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie vnto vs, it ſhould teach vs to giue vnto the Lorde the honour and praiſe of our preſeruation: that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding wee haue ſo many thouſand mightie, and craftie, and malicious aduerſaries, yet wee liue in ſafetie, and doe enioy innumerable bleſſings of God to our great comfort: that albeit the diuell comes neer vs, yet he cannot hurt vs: and though this rauenous wolfe be euen in the middeſt of the flocke, yet hee cannot ſpoyle ſo much as one lambe among them: and that howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer there bee multitudes of his Adherents, that haue a deadly quarrell againſt pietie, and againſt the vpholders and maintainers thereof, ſo that no Lyon is more gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of his prey, then they are of the blood of Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, yet wee enioy our health, and ſtrength, and food, and families, and libertie of calling vpon the name of the Lord: for this wonderfull fauour of our good God, in reſtraining the diuell &amp; his inſtruments from doing vs miſchiefe, we ſhould neuer ceaſe to magnifie his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious name: euermore endeuouring to keep our ſelues
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19247:7"/> in his fauour, that ſo he being with vs, and ſtanding for vs, we may not neede to feare any of our aduerſaries that intend hurt and violence againſt vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But if thou canſt doe any thing,</hi>] In that this man makes a doubt whether Chriſt can helpe his child, or not, and ſo manifeſts his infidelitie, albeit he was otherwiſe a godly man: this doctrine may be collected hence, that</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> 2. The faithfull tainted with vnbeliefe.</note> Gods owne children with their faith, haue ſome mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of vnbeliefe.</p>
               <p>That this man was a beleeuer, may appeare by ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie circumſtances of the text: as namely, that he came vnto Chriſt his diſciples for helpe, and when he found none at their hands, did not depraue, nor diſgrace them, but went vnto our Sauiour, and that not onely to haue his ſonne helped, but to haue his owne vnbeliefe cured, giuing him this honour, to be the author and worker of grace in the hearts of the ſonnes of men: yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all this, he herein manifeſted his infirmitie, that he made queſtion of Chriſt his power, whether he could caſt the diuell out of his child or not.</p>
               <p>The ſcripture is plentifull of teſtimonies for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of this point. <note place="margin">Gen. 12. Gen. 28. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Abraham</hi> was the father of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuers, and had a full parſwaſion in ſome particulars: yet how weake did he ſhew himſelfe, when he expoſed his wife to euident perill of violating her chaſtitie, by cauſing her to ſay that ſhe was his ſiſter, that ſo his life might be ſpared, which otherwiſe might be endangered (as he thought) by reaſon of her beautie? as if the Lord could not as well protect him in <hi>Gerar,</hi> and in <hi>Egipt,</hi> as he had done in <hi>Canaan,</hi> and in <hi>Meſopotamia!</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 16.</note> So alſo in another particular: the Lord promiſed that he ſhould haue a child by <hi>Sarah,</hi> but he had waited long, and the promiſe was not yet fulfilled, and now <hi>Sarah</hi> was alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether vnlikely (in the ordinarie courſe of nature) to beare a child: in this caſe what doth <hi>Abraham?</hi> at the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19247:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> perſwaſion of his wife, hee takes <hi>Hagar,</hi> that ſo <hi>Sarah</hi> might haue a ſonne by her: as if God had beene in a ſtraite, and knewe not how to bee as good as his word, vnles the promiſe might beare this conſtruction, that <hi>Sarah</hi> ſhould haue a child indeed, but by another, this was great vnbeliefe in him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dauid</hi> likewiſe had commonly an excellent faith, <note place="margin">1. Sam. 24. &amp; 26. 9.</note> in ſo much that when <hi>Saul</hi> his enemie was in his handes, ſo that hee might haue ſlaine him, and was vrged by his men ſo to doe, or to ſuffer them to doe it, yet hee would in no wiſe yeeld vnto them, to take away <hi>Sauls</hi> life; but reſolued to waite vpon the Lord, who would take him away in due time, either by a naturall, or by a violent death, and aduance him to the Kingdome in his ſteede: yet after this good reſolution, he manifeſted great frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and weaknes of faith: <note place="margin">1. Sam. 27. 1.</note> for <hi>he ſaid in his heart, I ſhall now periſh one day by the hand of Saul:</hi> and therevpon he fled vnto the King of <hi>Gath,</hi> and there beeing in perill of his life, bewrayed much infidelitie before the king.</p>
               <p>And the like corruption doth our Sauiour oft times reprehend in his Diſciples, <note place="margin">Matth. 8. 26. Luk. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Why did you feare, ô yee of little faith?</hi> ſaith hee; and as theſe particular examples do e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidently proue the point in hand, ſo alſo doth the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall example of the whole Church, of which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaketh thus: <note place="margin">Iſaiah. 49. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Zion ſaid, the Lord hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken mee, and my Lord hath forgotten mee;</hi> if they had af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed that God had reiected but one member of his Church; though it were but one of the meaneſt, as it were the little finger, it had beene a great diſhonour vnto his Name; but that hee ſhould caſt off his whole Church, was a charge farre more hainous and intollerable: and argued a great meaſure of vnbeliefe in Gods people, that either ſaid it, or thought it. Yet the Lord doth not diſcourage them for this, but rather vſeth arguments to confirme and ſtrengthen them. <hi>Can a woman</hi> (ſaith he) <note place="margin">Verſ. 15.</note>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:19247:8"/>
                  <note place="margin">Verſe. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>forget her childe, and not haue compaſſion on the ſonne of her wombe? though they ſhould forget, yet will not I forget thee.</hi> In which words the Lord telleth them for their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, that a mother, that hath a child ſucking on her breaſts, may ſooner forſake it, and forget that ſhe hath ſuch an one, than he can relinquiſh them, and let his choſen ones ſlippe out of his minde.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſons.</note> Now the reaſon why the remnants of infidelitie doe ſtill remaine in ſuch as are Gods faithfull ſeruants, are theſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">1</note> Firſt, becauſe there is in the beſt a great defect of knowledge, as the Apoſtle witneſſeth: 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 12. and certaine it is, that we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not beleeue more than we know, though we may know more than we beleeue: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our knowledge being but weake and imperfect, our faith cannot be abſolute and perfect.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">2</note> Secondly, there is no other grace of God, but is ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with imperfections, and therefore faith cannot be perfect; for if it were, it would perfect all the reſt of the vertues that are in vs: our humilitie would be without any pride: our patience without any diſcontentment: our loue without any manner of bitterneſſe, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">3</note> Thirdly, it is a good prouidence of God that it ſhould be ſo; for otherwiſe his wonderfull mercie in bearing with vs, and his mightie hand in vpholding vs, would not ſo euidently be ſeene: we could not elſe ſo eaſily parceiue how ſtrong the Lord is, in fenſing vs againſt dangerous temptations; in deliuering vs from violent corruptions: in arming vs againſt boiſterous perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and in vpholding vs in all manner of tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Vſe. 1.</note> Let this therefore firſt of all be an inſtruction vnto vs, to teach vs to be more ſparing in our cenſures, when we finde defects of faith, either in our ſelues or others. The beſt of Gods ſeruants (as hath beene ſufficiently
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19247:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> prooued) are ſubiect to many doubtings, both concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the promiſes of God, and concerning his proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence: and therefore when we finde the like in our ſelues or others, let vs not thereupon conclude, that we are not of the number of the faithfull: for we may haue a true iuſtifying faith at that very inſtant, when we are full of doubting touching ſome particular points; as may be ſeene in the examples before alleaged for the confirmation of this doctrine: and if God ſhould worke all at once in vs, there would be no more imployment for him; nor any further vſe of the meanes of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. Let vs not therefore diſcourage our hearts, as if we had no faith, becauſe we finde defects in our faith: or as if we had nothing elſe but infirmities, becauſe we finde ſome infirmities in our ſelues: Chriſt deales more charitable than ſo with <hi>Peter:</hi> for though he were afraid vpon the ſight of a great waue, after that Chriſt had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him experience of his power, in making him able to walke vpon the ſea, yet doth he not call him vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuer, or faithles perſon: but ſaith vnto him, <note place="margin">Math. 14. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>Why did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt thou feare, ô thou of little faith?</hi> giuing him his due, that he had ſome faith; albeit he had not ſo much as he ſhould haue had.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Vſe. 2.</note> Secondly, is it ſo, that the beſt haue ſome dregges of vnbeliefe ſtill remaining in them? then let vs be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding carefull in looking to our owne hearts, for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe we may fall very dangerouſly. Let vs not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore preſume vpon this, that we haue faith, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſhall alwaies ſtand vpright: for though we haue a wonderfull excellent faith, as <hi>Abraham</hi> had, and as <hi>Dauid</hi> had, yet we may ſuddenly ſlippe into ſcandalous offences, as they did, becauſe we haue infidelitie as a dangerous traytour ſtill harbouring within vs, which hath many ill companions attending vpon it, and is readie ſtill to ſhew it ſelfe in diſtempered paſſions, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19247:9"/> inordinate courſes, vnleſſe wee doe maruellous careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie reſtraine and repreſſe the motions thereof. Little though <hi>Peter</hi> euer to denie and forſweare his maiſter, when hee was ſo reſolute, that he ſtood vpon it with our Sauiour, that though hee ſhould die with him, yet hee would neuer forſake him; yet we reade what his vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe brought him vnto. Wee are of the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that hee was, let vs therefore bee admoniſhed by his example, that when <hi>wee thinke that wee ſtand, wee take heede leaſt wee fall:</hi> for though wee be neuer ſo va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorous in our owne conceits, little doe wee know in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to what crueltie, and into what bitternes of ſpeech wee may breake forth, and how exceeding cowardlie wee may ſhew our ſelues in the cauſes of God: the ſerious conſideration whereof, ſhould cauſe vs euermore to haue an eye vnto our vnbeliefe, and to looke narrowly therevnto: yea, to lay ſtrong chaines vpon it, and to keepe it cloſe priſoner: for otherwiſe, it will make ſome ſcape or other, and comming abroade, will play ſuch leaud trickes, as will bring ſhame vnto vs, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour vnto God, and a blemiſh vpon our holie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Helpe vs, and haue compaſſion on vs;</hi> that is, on mee and my childe: Whence ariſeth this doctrine, that</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> 3. Loue makes men to beare others burde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, as if they were their owne.</note> True loue will cauſe men to make their caſe for whom they pray to be their owne. It will make them to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with their eſtate, for whom they become ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters vnto the Lord, and to beare a burden with them in their afflictions: as heere we ſee in this man, who made his ſonnes caſe and his owne alike.</p>
               <p>Thus doth the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> make himſelfe a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, when hee dealeth with the Lorde in the behalfe of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> againſt whom Gods wrath was kindled, <hi>Our treſpaſſes are manie before thee</hi> (ſaith hee) <note place="margin">Iſa. 59. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>and our ſinnes teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie againſt vs.</hi> And againe, chapt. 64. 6. <hi>Wee haue beene</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:19247:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                  <hi>as an vncleane thing, and our righteouſnes as filthie cloutes, &amp;c.</hi> In the like ſort ſpeaketh the Prophet <hi>Ieremie;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ierem. 14. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>O Lord, though our iniquities testifie againſt vs</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>deale with vs according to thy name: for our rebellions are manie, wee haue ſinned againſt thee.</hi> So doeth <hi>Daniel</hi> alſo, <note place="margin">Daniel. 9. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Wee haue ſinned</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and haue committed iniquitie, and haue done wickedly; yea, wee haue rebelled, and haue departed from thy precepts, and from thy iudgements.</hi> And laſtlie, (not to heape together moe examples of this kinde) good <hi>Ezra</hi> manifeſteth the like holy affection, as thoſe before-named did; for thus hee prayeth, <note place="margin">Ezra. 9. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>O my GOD, I am confounded, and aſhamed to lift vp mine eyes vnto thee my God: for our iniquities are increaſed ouer our head, and our treſpaſſe is growen vp vnto the heauen.</hi> In which exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples we ſee, that thoſe holie men of God, though they were very innocent of any hainous crime, and in reſpect of thoſe faults, which they for whom they prayed were guiltie of, altogether blameleſſe, and vntainted, yet they tooke to heart the offences committed by others, as if had beene principall men in the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſons.</note> The reaſons why Gods children muſt bee thus affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, are theſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">1.</note> Firſt, becauſe this fellow-feeling of others miſeries, is a verie effectuall meanes to make them feruent and earneſt in their ſuites and requeſts: as the examples be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alleaged, doe clearely manifeſt. Whereas on the contrarie, if men doe not much care for others calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as if they did nothing at all, or verie little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne them; they will pray, but very coldlie and drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilie for them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">2</note> Secondly, as this ſenſiblenes of other mens diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, will make Gods ſeruants feruent, ſo will it alſo make them conſtant in their prayers for them: ſo that after many delayes and repulſes, they will ſtill perſeuere in making ſupplication for them: but on the other ſide, if
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19247:10"/> men be not thus affected toward them, they will quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be diſcouraged, and ſoone let their ſuite fall to the ground: as we may obſerue in the diſciples of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, who ſpeaking for the woman of <hi>Canaan,</hi> without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great ſenſe and feeling of her miſerie, were very cold and ſhort in their requeſt. Maiſter (ſay they) <hi>ſend her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way:</hi> that is, diſpatch her, that ſhe may be gone, for <hi>ſhe cryeth after vs.</hi> Now when Chriſt anſwered that <note place="margin">Math. 15. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>he was not ſent vnto the loſt ſheepe of the houſe of Iſrael,</hi> their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er was at an end, and they had no more to ſay for her: but the poore woman, being thoroughly afflicted with the torment of her daughter, would not let the matter paſſe ſo, but replyeth vpon Chriſt Ieſus, and anſwereth euery one of his obiections, till at length her requeſt was granted.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">3</note> Thirdly, this will cauſe their prayers to be effectuall, and to finde good admittance and acceptance with the Lord: they cannot but be welcome vnto him, in regard they proceed from abundance of loue, and of tender compaſſion in the parties, which are graces wherewith the Lord is well pleaſed, yea, and much delighted.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">4</note> Fourthly, as others ſhall haue the benefite of ſuch prayers, ſo ſhal they the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues that make them haue the comfort thereof in a ſpeciall manner: As <hi>Ieremie,</hi> and <hi>Daniel,</hi> and ſuch like holy men, who vpon the granting of their requeſts, had an hundred times more conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, than ordinarie people for whom they prayed: and if it ſo fall out that our requeſts be not granted in the particulars, yet ſhall we ſome way or other be propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionably recompenced by the Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">5</note> Laſtly, if no other reaſon would induce vs, yet the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of our bleſſed Sauiour ſhould moue vs to this holy communicating with the miſeries of our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: for he tooke our perſons vpon him, and <note place="margin">2. Cor. 5. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>he that knew no ſinne, was made ſinne for vs, that we might be made</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:19247:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                  <hi>the righteouſnes of God, through him.</hi> He became our ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and tooke vpon him both the guiltineſſe and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of our ſinnes: he did not onely pittie vs, and ſpeake for vs, but alſo dealt for vs, and died for vs: and therefore it behooueth vs to <note place="margin">Phil. 2. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>put on the ſame minde that was in Chriſt Ieſus:</hi> and to bee affected in the like ſort as he was. <note place="margin" type="runSum">Vſe 1.</note> Which maketh for the iuſt reproofe of thoſe, who when they are petitioners vnto God for others, deale no otherwiſe then great mens Attendants com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly do, for ſuch as haue before hand hired them to preferre their ſuites vnto their maiſters: or then cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Lawiers doe for their Clients, when they haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued their fees: they thinke they ſhall looſe nothing if matters go againſt them: nor gaine any thing if they ſucceed for them: and therefore they vſe not much ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerneſſe in the purſuite thereof, but deale coldlie and careleſly in the cauſes which they vndertake: So doe a great manie in their ſuites which they put vp vnto God; yea, euen then when they are to ſpeake for their owne children, or other neere friends: and that when they are in a moſt lamentable taking, ſo that they might iuſtly ſay as the woman of <hi>Canaan</hi> did of her daughter, <hi>O Lord haue mercie on mee;</hi> my childe, or my friend, is <note place="margin">Matth. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>miſerablie vexed with a diuell:</hi> miſerablie haunted with pride, with vncleanneſſe, with voluptuouſnes, &amp;c: Yet Satan doth as it were, bellow forth at their mouthes, and is ready to caſt them (not into the water, or into the fire, as was this mans childe, but) euen into hell fire, which neuer ſhall bee quenched: albeit (I ſay) the caſe ſtand thus with manie mens children, or friendes: Nay fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, though they haue beene brought to this paſſe by their ill educating of them, or their giuing of ill exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple vnto them, yet when they are to make ſupplication vnto the Lord for them, they are maruellous remiſſe and cold in the ſame: thereby ſhewing, that their praiers
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19247:11"/> proceed from their lips, rather than from their hearts. Nay, in the caſe of Gods Church, whereof they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues are members, or at leaſt profeſſe themſelues ſo to be, they aske ſo careleſly and drowſily, as if it did no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all pertaine vnto them, whether the <hi>Goſpell haue a free paſſage</hi> or not; whether Gods ordinances be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed in ſinceritie and puritie or not; whether Gods ſeruants continue in their vprightneſſe or not, &amp;c. This is a fault ſharpely to be cenſured in ſuch as make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the truth, and we haue all cauſe much to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne our ſelues for our great fayling in this behalfe: and to labour hereafter to put on the bowels of tender compaſſion, that ſo wee may make othres caſes our owne, and mourne for their calamities, and for their tranſgreſſions, as if they were our owne.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">2</note> Secondly, is it ſo, that chriſtian loue will cauſe men to partake with others in their diſtreſſes, as if they were theirs? then here is matter of ſpeciall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolation vnto all the Saints of God: for there is neuer a one of them, but hath ſundrie others to beare his burden, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with him in all his ſorrowes and anguiſhes. And therefore, let them not be vtterly diſmaied, albeit they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not take their owne caſe to heart as they would, and as they ſhould: if they be inwardly grieued that they are ſo ſenſleſſe of the ſtroakes of God vpon them, they may take this for their comfort, that God will paſſe by their infirmitie, and accept of the ſeruencie of others prayers in their behalfe, who are more earneſt with God for them, than they can be for themſelues. Thus much concerning the mans petition: our Sauiours anſwere followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="sermon">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:19247:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>The ſecond Sermon.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>VERSE 23.</bibl>
                     <p>If thou canſt beleeue, all things are poſſible to the beleeuer.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Eere wee muſt note, that when it is ſaid, <hi>If thou canſt beleeue, &amp;c:</hi> The meaning is not, that Chriſt could not heale his childe vnleſſe hee did beleeue: for mans diſabilitie doth nothing diminiſh Gods abilitie: but this is ſpoken by our Sauiour to helpe the mans faith; hee knew well enough that hee did in part beleeue, but hee would haue him ſearch, and trie his heart, and ſet his faith a worke before hee would graunt his requeſt. Whence wee may note this Doctrine, that</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> 1. Chriſt begins with the heart.</note> Where Chriſt Ieſus doth helpe anie one in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, hee firſt helps his heart, and layes the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his worke in his ſoule. This courſe hee tooke with <hi>Marthae</hi> and <hi>Marie,</hi> when hee would gratifie them with a ſpeciall fauour, in reſtoring to life their dead bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which was very deere vnto them; <note place="margin">Iohn. 11.</note> Hee firſt of all labours to ſtrengthen their faith in this point, that hee was able to raiſe him out of the graue againe: yea,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19247:12"/> though hee had beene foure dayes dead.</p>
               <p>In the like ſort dealt the Lord with the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Acts. 27.</note> when he and the reſt that were with him, had bene four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene dayes toſſed with a ſore and dangerous tempeſt, looking euer and anon, when they ſhould bee drowned in the Sea, and all that while had eaten nothing, feare hauing taken away their ſtomachs. In this extremitie God ſent his Angell vnto <hi>Paul,</hi> not giuing him preſent deliuerance, but telling him that hee and the reſt ſhould be deliuered, that ſo their faith might be exerciſed by depending on his promiſe, and the benefite might bee more acceptable when it came. The like may be ſaid of <hi>Iehoſhaphats</hi> caſe, when ſuch huge armies of enemies came againſt him: <note place="margin">2. Chron. 20. 14. 15.</note> it was then time (wee would haue thought) for the Lord to ſet vpon his aduerſaries, and to ouerthrowe their forces: but hee firſt of all ſends king <hi>Iehoſhaphat,</hi> and the reſt of the people, a Prophet to fitte and prepare their hearts, for ſuch a wonderfull victorie, as afterward hee gaue them; and that made it to bee a farre greater bleſſing, then otherwiſe it could haue beene.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſons.</note> And the reaſon why God doth firſt helpe the heart, is,</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">1</note> Firſt, becauſe otherwiſe the benefite that he beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, would bee but momentanie: for either the thing it ſelfe ſhould be taken away, or elſe ſome miſchiefe enſue vpon the hauing of it, ſo that it would ceaſe to bee a bleſſing. Hence is it, that the Lord ſaith vnto <hi>Ahaz,</hi> and his people, after hee had promiſed them deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from their enemies; <note place="margin">Iſa. 7. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>If yee beleeue not, ſurely yee ſhall not bee eſtabliſhed.</hi> And therefore was it, <note place="margin">1. Kings. 20.</note> that though wicked <hi>Ahab</hi> were ſaued from the ſword of the king of <hi>Aram,</hi> at one time, yet hee got little by it: for hauing no grace in his heart, <note place="margin">1. Kings. 22.</note> hee was wounded in fighting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Aramites</hi> another time, ſo that his Charret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man carried him out of the hoaſt, vnto <hi>Samaria,</hi> and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19247:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> death carried him from thence vnto hell, the proper place of ſuch ſinfull rebels as he was.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">2</note> Secondly, when mens hearts are well fitted for a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, it becomes a double bleſſing vnto them. For it doth not alone helpe them for their preſent ſtate, but alſo for their eternall ſtate: not onely for this life, but for euerlaſting life: not for the preſent alone, but for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer after, they being aſſured, that God is alwaies the ſame in grace and fauour towards his children.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Vſe. 1.</note> Therefore if at any time we deſire any bleſſing, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance for our ſelues, or our friends, out of dangers, or debts, or the like, let vs intreate the Lord firſt of all to applie his medicine to the due place. We ſee it ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie with skilfull phyſitians in the curing of many diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, that though the ſickneſſe be in the head, or in any other part, yet they conueigh their phyſicke into the ſtomach. So let vs beſeech the Lord that he will deale with vs, or with ſuch as are neere vnto vs: that he will beginne his cure in our heart, which is the ſtomacke of the ſoule: which being ſoundly healed, we ſhall finde, not onely the fit ſtaied for the preſent, but the ſicknes preuented for afterwards.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">2</note> Secondly, let the wiſedome of Chriſt in his dealing with this man, ſerue for our imitation: Are we minded to doe our neighbours a good turne in outward re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, for their bodie, or for their eſtate, or for his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren? let vs in the firſt place labour as farre as God hath inabled vs, to helpe their hearts; to increaſe their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; to ſtrengthen their faith in Gods promiſes and prouidence, and to miniſter vnto them ſpirituall refreſhing as well as corporall. And thus taking the ſame courſe with our friends in their ſickneſſes, and in their diſtreſſe, as our Sauiour did, we may the more comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably expect a full recompence of our worke from the righteous Iudge of heauen and earth; and withall, we
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19247:13"/> ſhall haue this teſtimonie vnto our ſoules, that we doe not good things in a carnall manner, nor for fleſhly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, but with an vpright heart, and to a right end, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring principally that God may be glorified in the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the parties, to whom our beautie and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is extended.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">3</note> Thirdly, ſeeing that the Lord vſeth to begin his worke in the hart, where he purpoſeth to vouchſafe any outward bleſſing in mercie: Let this teach vs not to be impatient, nor to thinke it too long, ere God beſtow a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny benefit vpon vs: but let vs rather looke into our ſelues, and ſuſpect our owne preparation and fitneſſe to be partakers of any ſpeciall fauour from the Lord.</p>
               <p>Will not our aduerſaries be pacified toward vs, nor reconciled vnto vs? Let vs examine whether we haue made peace with the Lord, and procured his louing countenance to ſhine vpon vs: otherwiſe we may cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely conclude, that all our enemies heate is but a ſparke of his diſpleaſure againſt vs. Are our outward wants &amp; neceſſities many &amp; great, and of long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance? let vs make triall whether they doe not proceed from want of religion; from want of ſinceritie before the Lord, &amp; of a godly, and honeſt conuerſation before men: haue we great imbecilitie in our bodies, and doe we finde a ſenſible decay of our health? let vs ſearch whether the weakeneſſe of our faith haue not beene the cauſe of it, in that we haue not conſcionably vſed the meanes that God hath appointed for the confirming therof: and whether we haue not declined in the courſe of our obedience, and beene too well content to feele an inward decay of Gods graces, for which Gods hand hath lighted vpon our outward man. And if we deale thus, we ſhall be driuen to accuſe our ſelues, rather than to murmur againſt God, and ſo fitting our ſelues for mercie, we ſhall finde it at his hands in due ſeaſon, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19247:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> that to our greater comfort, then if wee had obtained it ſooner.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If thou canſt belieue, &amp;:</hi>] In that our Sauiour makes a doubt hereof, &amp; that not without cauſe, the doctrine is, that, <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> 2. No man hath faith at com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund.</note> It is not in any mans owne power to beleeue when hee will, and what hee will, and as much as he will.</p>
               <p>Faith is not at mens commaund: for if it had beene, our Sauiour would neuer haue propounded this queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: neither would the Diſciples haue left the child vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured, which now was brought vnto our Sauiour: for they were deſirous to doe what they could for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of their maiſter, for their owne credite and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and for the ſtopping of the mouthes of their bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter aduerſaries: Now the cauſe why they could not caſt out this diuell was (as their Maiſter tolde them) their vnbeliefe: not that they were vnwilling to beleeue, but that they were vnable to beleeue, vnleſſe they ſhould haue vſed faſting and prayer for the obtaining of faith, which they could not doe. And if anie deſire a proofe of this point, let him read the 17. chapt. of <hi>Luke,</hi> where the Apoſtles hearing our Sauiour deliuer this leſſon, that <hi>if our brother ſinne againſt vs ſeuen times in a day, and ſeuen times in a day turne againe vnto vs, ſaying, it repenteth mee: wee muſt forgiue him:</hi> they take occaſion thereby, to pray in this ſort: <note place="margin">Luk. 17. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord increaſe our faith.</hi> Which is in effect, as if they had ſaid; Lord, this is a dutie which is beyond our reach: our faith will not extend ſo farre, and therefore Lord, ſithence thou requireſt this at our hands, adde vnto that meaſure of faith which thou haſt giuen vs, that ſo wee may be able to performe it. Now if they could haue beleeued as much as they would, what need had they thus earneſtly to deſire an increaſe of their faith? Let this then be concluded for a certaine truth, that no man is able to attaine to what meaſure of faith it pleaſeth him. Neither is this ſo only at mens
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19247:14"/> firſt conuerſion, but afterwards alſo.</p>
               <p>For their firſt conuerſion, there is no doubt but it proceedeth wholie from God, and is his meere gift, according to that of our Sauiour, <note place="margin">Iohn. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>None can come vnto mee, except the father draw him.</hi> And that of the Apoſtle, <note place="margin">Phil. 1. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>Vnto you it is giuen for Chriſt, that not onely yee ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in him, but alſo ſuffer for his ſake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as for the ſtate of a Chriſtian after his conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, it is as plaine, that none can exerciſe his faith in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny particular without Gods ſpeciall aſſiſtance: as may be ſeene in the example of <hi>Abraham,</hi> who though he had a very excellent faith, yet when he came into a forren countrie among a barbarous people, it much failed him in that particular, that he could not reſt vpon Gods power and prouidence for the preſeruation of his life, but choſe rather to expoſe his wife to danger, by ſaying that ſhe <hi>was his ſiſter.</hi> Otherwiſe he thought, that though they were not ſo monſtrouſly wicked (as many now a daies are) as to abuſe his wife, he being aliue, yet they would kill him, that ſo they might freely take her vnto themſelues. Here we ſee carnall reaſon did oppoſe it ſelfe againſt his faith, and in this particular ouerſwaied him. And ſo it was with <hi>Zacharie,</hi> the husband of <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet</hi> (though ouerwiſe a true beleeuer) when he heard of the Angell that he ſhould haue a ſonne in his old age he was ſo intangled with carnall conceites, that he could not giue credit thereto: I am olde (ſaith he) <note place="margin">Luke. 1. 18.</note> and my wife is olde, and is it poſſible that ſuch olde people as we are ſhould haue a childe? And in the ſame caſe did <hi>Sarah</hi> faile, though ſhe were the <hi>Matriarch</hi> of holy women, <note place="margin">Gen. 18. 12.</note> when ſhe was tolde that ſhe ſhould beare a ſonne, ſhe laughed at it, as if it were a ridiculous thing to beleeue any ſuch matter: and as carnall reaſon doth hinder the faith of Gods ſeruants, ſo alſo doe diſtempered paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as anger and feare, and the like. As we may note in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19247:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                  <hi>Moſes,</hi> though an admirable man, and ſuch an one as in other caſes had ſhewed a care and worthie faith, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vexed and troubled at the rebellious diſpoſition of the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> he manifeſted great vnbeliefe: for when God promiſed him to feede all that people for a moneth with fleſh in the wildernes, he doubted how it could be: What (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aith he) <note place="margin">Nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 11. 21. 22</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall all the beastes be killed for hem? and ſhall all the fiſhes of the Sea be gathered together, to make prouiſion for them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> As if God had ouerſhot him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, in making them ſuch a large promiſe, as he would not be able to ſtand too.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Vſe 1.</note> Heere then are they to bee confuted, that neuer had anie faith at all, and yet thinke that they can beleeue whatſoeuer God telleth them: yea, they make that an argument of the ſtrength of their faith, that they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade themſelues they can beleeue at their pleaſure: I dare vndertake (ſay they) that I doe beleeue, and will beleeue; that I doe repent, and will repent; (both which come to one reckoning) and that as well as the proudeſt of them: and therein they ſay true indeed, as well as the proudeſt; for the proud beleeue not at all, but haue the Lord himſelfe <note place="margin">Iam. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>to reſiſt them, when hee giueth grace to the humble:</hi> Neither haue ſuch boaſters any faith at all; for if they knew what it meant, they would neuer ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume vpon their owne ſtrength.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Vſe. 2.</note> Secondly, let this teach vs when wee goe about any ſeruice of God, not to reſt vpon that olde ſtore of faith which we haue, nor to be ſo confident thereof; as to ſay, If now I were to heare the word, or to be partaker of the Sacrament, I am ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly prouided without any more adoe: or if this or that croſſe ſhould fall vpon mee, I haue vndergone greater matters then that comes too; and therefore I know I ſhall not ſhrinke vnder it. Let vs not (I ſay) thus builde vpon our owne ſtrength, but let euery one rather come to this, my faith is not mine
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19247:15"/> owne, I cannot beleeue what &amp; when I will, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Lord make me to beleeue whatſoeuer is needfull, according as occaſion ſhall be offered; if we doe not thus, we ſhall finde by wofull experience, that though we haue the ſhield of faith, yet when we come into the field againſt our aduerſaries, we ſhall not be able to vſe it, either to Gods glorie, or our owne ſafegard.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>All things are poſſible to him that beleeueth.</hi>] If faith be ſet a worke, nothing is ſo hard and difficult, but it will goe thorough therewith: whence obſerue this doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, that</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> 3. The faithfull are ſtrongeſt and happieſt.</note> Of all the men in the world godly beleeuers are the moſt mightie and moſt happie.</p>
               <p>None haue ſo great power, nor ſo good an eſtate, as the faithfull, for they conquer the world: that is, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall corruptions, and outward allurements: according to that of the Apoſtle <hi>Iohn,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Iohn. 5. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>This is our victorie, whereby we ouercome the world, euen our faith.</hi> Without this it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for men to get victorie ouer themſelues and ouer their worldly luſts, be they neuer ſo great and mightie in the earth: nay the mightier they are, the weaker in this conflict: the world hath them in the greateſt ſeruitude of all others: it puts them as it were into the dungeon, and holdes them faſt in the ſtockes, and makes them the moſt miſerable bondſlaues that are, vnto pride, and ſenſualitie, and all kinde of voluptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>2</label> Againe, as faith makes men conquerers ouer the world, ſo doth it alſo ouer the diuell, for <note place="margin">1. Pet. 5. 9. Iam. 4. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>if we reſiſt him ſtedfaſt in the faith, he will flie from vs.</hi> And concerning all other difficulties, let vs reade the 11. <hi>Chap.</hi> of the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> where the wonderfull and ſtrange effects of faith are at large ſpoken of; and there we ſhall eaſily perceiue, that the moſt incredible things that can be imagined, haue by vertue thereof beene effected,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19247:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> and accompliſhed. <note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſons.</note> And the reaſon hereof is,</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">1.</note> Firſt, becauſe faithfull men doe lay holde of God himſelfe, and of his all-ſufficiencie; and therfore hauing the enioyment of his fauour, what can be wanting vnto them?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">2</note> Secondly, they build vpon the truth of God: for faith is not euery ſlight imagination of a frenticke braine, but a ſetled perſwaſion, grounded on the word of God: and therefore if the ſcriptures ſay ſimplie and without exception, that they ſhall haue any thing, they reſt vpon it, without any wauering: but if the ſcriptures promiſe with condition onely, they doe conditionally expect the things ſo promiſed: and by this meanes their happineſſe is as large as Gods promiſes; and their hopes are ratified by the truth of his word, <note place="margin">Numb. 23. 23.</note> who is not as man <hi>that he ſhould lie:</hi> and of whom it is ſaid, <note place="margin">Rom. 3. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Let God be free,</hi> and <hi>euery man a liar.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Vſe. 1.</note> Seeing then that there is ſuch efficacie in faith, and ſuch happineſſe depending thereon, let vs preferre it before all earthly treaſures, and count all the glorie of the world baſe in compariſon of it: for a poore faithfull Chriſtian, is better then a rich vnbeleeuing king: And why? becauſe all things are poſſible vnto him; he may haue his hearts deſire in any thing, ſo farre as his affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is ordered by Gods word: and this priuiledge haue none in the world, but only beleeuers.</p>
               <p>It is no where in the ſcripture ſaid, All things are poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the rich, to the noble, to thoſe that are ſtrong, or to thoſe that are couragious: nay ſuch doe continually finde, that their willes and deſires are exceedingly croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and that it is impoſſible for them to bring many of their enterpriſes to paſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 4.</note> as great as he was, fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d by experience that al things are not poſſible to the mightie <hi>Monarches</hi> of the earth; and that when they begin to exalt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19247:16"/> into the place of God, as hee did, the Lorde can quickly cauſe a great King to be in farre worſe caſe then the baſeſt beggar, as indeed hee was; being ſtript of his kingdome, of his wittes, and of all earthly comforts, euen on a ſudden, when hee litle feared any ſuch matter. Sithence therefore the caſe ſtands thus, that no world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie preheminence or excellencie, can yeelde men that contentment, which faith will doe, what remaineth, but that wee ſet the higheſt price vpon that which is of the greateſt worth: and aboue all things ſeeke for that, which will make vs moſt happie, when wee haue found it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">2</note> Secondly, if we deſire friends that are able, and willing, and euery way ſufficient to ſtand vs in ſteed, let vs en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour to bee in league with ſuch as haue the greateſt meaſure of faith, and to make them our chiefeſt friends, who are moſt godly &amp; moſt faithful people. <hi>Peter</hi> found the benefite hereof: <note place="margin">Acts 12.</note> he had many mortall aduerſaries, as <hi>Herode,</hi> and the whole power of the <hi>Romanes,</hi> and the ſtate of the <hi>Iewes:</hi> and what friends had he to ſtand for him? a poore companie of men and women, that durſt not ſhewe their heads, for feare of their enemies; who yet by the force of their prayers, preuailed more for him, then all the aduerſe power could againſt him: for when they ſpake vnto God in his behalfe, neither the priſon, nor his chaines, nor the ſouldiers, nor any power whatſoeuer, could keepe him any longer in hold: but the Lord ſent his Angell, and freed him out of the hands of ſuch as hated him, and purpoſed the next day to haue taken his life from him.</p>
               <p>And as the faith of Gods ſeruants is very mightie for their frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds deliuera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: ſo is it as effectuall for the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of their enemies: as may be ſeene in <hi>Haman,</hi> who ſoared ſo high aboue the reach of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> that in all likelyhood none of them could come neere him: But
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19247:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Heſter</hi> &amp; <hi>Mordecai,</hi> and the reſt of the faithfull, ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned together in faſting and prayer, their faith pulled him downe vnto the ground, and layd all his honour in the very duſt. Whence it is euident and cleere to thoſe that haue any vnderſtanding, how needfull and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall a thing it is, to haue godly men on our ſide; and and therefore if wee would be eſteemed trulie wiſe, let vs ioyne our ſelues in moſt inward friendſhip and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaritie with them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Vſe. 3.</note> Thirdly, if nothing be impoſſible to beleeuers, then is it not impoſſible for them to maiſter &amp; ſubdue their ſtrongeſt corruptions: and therefore let not the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full bee diſcouraged, though they find themſelues as yet very worldly minded, very angrie and paſſionate, very vaine-glorious, and ambitious, &amp;c: If they will ſet their faith a worke, they ſhall get victorie ouer theſe and the like corrupt affections: and albeit they haue prayed of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten againſt them, and yet finde ſmall ſtrength to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come them, let them not giue ouer the combatte, for faith will haue the better in the ende. And the like may be ſaid for all manner of croſſes: it will either make an vtter riddance of them, or at leaſt furniſh vs with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and abilitie to vndergoe them.</p>
               <p>Verſ. 24. <hi>And ſtraight-way the father of the childe crying with teares, ſayd, &amp;c:</hi> Hence this doctrine might be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> 4. See in Clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Sermon, on Lament. 3. Doct. 1.</note> Faith and godlie ſorrow may well goe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: for both of theſe are apparant in this faithfull man: and Gods children haue oftentimes, and almoſt continually occaſion of this holie griefe, in reſpect of themſelues, and in reſpect of Gods Church: in reſpect of corruptions, and of afflictions, either priuate or pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, or both. But I will not now inſiſt vpon this point.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lord, I beleeue</hi>] Whence ariſeth this Doctrine, that <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> 5. Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s muſt ſee &amp; acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge their graces.</note> It is not vnlawfull, nor vncomely, for a Chriſtian to make profeſſion of his owne graces, though imperfect,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19247:17"/> if it be done in due time and manner.</p>
               <p>He may ſpeake of them vnto God or vnto men as occaſion is offered. So did this man here, <hi>Lord, I beleeue.</hi> So did <hi>Dauid,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 86. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Preſerue thou my ſoule, for I am mercifull.</hi> So did <hi>Ezekiah</hi> alſo, <note place="margin">Iſai. 38. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>I beſeech thee ô Lord, remember now how I haue walked before thee in truth, and with a perfect heart, and haue done that which is good in thy ſight.</hi> The ſcripture aboundes with examples of this kinde. <note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſons.</note> But let vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of ſome reaſons, as namely, that</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">1</note> Firſt, this muſt be done, becauſe it tendes to the mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying of Gods name: whereas the deniall of his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, makes for his diſhonour, and argues a baſe account thereof in the parties that haue them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">2</note> Secondly, the acknowledgement of the vertues of Chriſt which we haue, is an effectuall meanes to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then our faith, to comfort our harts, &amp; to inable vs with feruencie to call vpon the Lord: whereas vpon the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of this dutie, all the contrarie effects do fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Vſe. 1.</note> Here then are Gods deere children to be put in minde of an ordinarie and daungerous fault that is in them: which is, that in the time of temptation they ſo farre giue place vnto Sathan, as to yeeld that they are hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, and that they haue no ſauing grace of God in them. Indeed they cannot denie but they haue hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore done many good things; but all (ſay they) was in vaine-glorie, or for ſome carnall reſpect or other: they muſt needs confeſſe that they haue had many comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table feelings, but now they feare al of them were meere illuſions. What a follie is this, &amp; what indignitie do we herein offer vnto the holy ſpirit of grace, whereby we are ſealed vnto the day of redemption? why ſhould we not rather be of <hi>Iobs</hi> reſolution, <hi>viz:</hi> neuer to part with our innocencie &amp; vprightnes while we liue, but though men accuſe vs, and Sathan aſſault vs, and our owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19247:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> charge many heauie things vpon vs, yet to ſtand to it vnto the death, that our hearts are ſincere and faithfull with the Lord our God: when by ſound proofes and arguments taken from the word, wee can confirme ſo much vnto our owne ſoules? For in truth wee haue farre better reaſon to ſtand vpon our ſpirituall right, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earthly men haue to defend their ciuill right. Now if ſome craftie and ſubtill aduerſarie ſhould come vnto a worldly wiſe man, &amp; tell him, that all his writings &amp; eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences are meere counterfeites, and of no worth at al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>: and that therefore he is but an Intruder into that which hee poſſeſſeth, would not hee (if hee be able) maintaine the goodnes of his euidences, and prooue that the ſeales are authentical, that his witneſſes are ſufficient, &amp; that all things elſe doe concurre, which may make for the proouing of his title and right, in the things which he holdeth? Much more then ſhould we ſtand to make good the Deedes that we haue for our ſoules, and for our aſſurance of the heauenly inheritance, which hath bene of olde purchaſed for vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Vſe 2.</note> Let this therefore in the ſecond place, ſerue for an inſtruction vnto vs, that we neuer ſhew our ſelues to be of ſuch a cowardly heart, as when wee haue ſpoken well, or done well, to depraue the ſame, by ſaying that we are no better then hypocrites; or by confeſſing in word or writing, that wee are faultie. Nay, let vs neuer for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe our righteouſneſſe, but iuſtifie our ſelues in our righteous wayes, and workes, and acknowledge (with thankfulnes and humilitie) whatſoeuer good things the Lord hath wrought in vs, or by vs; that ſo hee may haue his due praiſe, and wee ſuch found comfort as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth vnto well-doers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Helpe mine vnbeleefe:</hi>] The laſt Doctrine which ſhall be collected from this verſe, is this, that</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:19247:18"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> 6. Faith ſhewes men their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, and moues the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſeeke helpe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them.</note> It is the propertie of grace to ſhew men their corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, &amp; to ſtir them vp to ſeeke helpe againſt the ſame.</p>
               <p>As in this man it doth euidentlie appeare, who as hee had infidelitie in him, ſo hauing faith withall, had his infidelitie diſcouered, and his heart moued to ſeeke vnto Chriſt Ieſus, for ſtrength againſt it. The like may bee obſerued in the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> who finding his heart to be vexed, and turmoyled within him, firſt of all falleth to reaſon the matter with his owne ſoule, ſaying;<note place="margin">Pſal. 42. 5. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Why art thou caſt downe my ſoule, and why doeſt thou make a tumult within me?</hi> (for ſo much the word implyeth) he hauing grace in his heart, perceiued that vnbeliefe did as it were mutinie within him, and raiſe vp rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt the Lord: and therefore finding his owne diſabilitie, euery way to encounter the ſame, hee in the next verſe of that <hi>Pſalme,</hi> puts vp his complaint vnto the Lord againſt it; <hi>My God</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>my ſoule is caſt downe within mee, &amp;c.</hi> As if he ſhould haue ſaid, Lord, I finde my ſelfe too weake to preuaile againſt this cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and therefore graunt mee ſtrength to get the better of it.</p>
               <p>Againe in another <hi>Pſalme,</hi> to wit, the 77. <note place="margin">Pſal. 77. 10.</note> he beginneth very lamentably, as one vtterly out of heart, almoſt concluding that the Lord had quite forſaken him, and caſt him out of his ſeruice: but afterward he recouereth himſelfe, and concludeth that it was his infirmitie ſo to imagine, and thereupon laboureth to confirme his faith by conſidering of the times of olde, and of the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full workes of God, which he wrought for the good of his people in former ages. So alſo in the 73. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 73.</note> we may note how the Prophet taketh notice of his great infirmitie, in enuying at wicked mens proſperitie, and in the end goeth into the Sanctuarie to get helpe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. Likewiſe in the prophecie of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iſaiah. 63.</note> we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the like effect of grace in the people of God, <hi>viz:</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:19247:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> that they doe diſcerne of the hardneſſe of their owne hearts, and complaine vnto the Lord againſt it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſons.</note> Now the reaſons of this point are theſe;</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">1</note> Firſt, becauſe grace maketh men iudicious, and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them full of knowledge, and of heauenly vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, whereby they are inabled to deſcrie what is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe within them. Gods gracious ſpirit whereſoeuer it comes, brings a light in his hand, whereby all things that are noyſome, or vnhandſome in the houſe, are plainely ſeene and diſcouered: ſo that thereby men are made able to iudge betwixt truth, and falſhood, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt good and euill.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">2</note> Secondly, as grace doth inlighten the minde, ſo doth it alſo ſanctifie the affections of the parties in whom it is. So that ſeeing what is good, they ſhall long for it, and earneſtly deſire it: &amp; diſcerning what is euill, they ſhall hate it, and flie from it. As it brings light with it, ſo it makes men to bee of a neate diſpoſition, that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not endure any thing that is fulſome and loathſome in their ſoules.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">5</note> Thirdly, grace maketh men induſtrious, and readie to put themſelues into the battle againſt their corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: Whereſoeuer faith is, it is working and effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall. 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1. 3.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">4</note> Fourthly, and laſtly, it maketh men full of courage and fortitude, ſo that they will neuer endure to haue ſinne raigne in their mortall bodies, but will maintaine perpetuall warre againſt the ſame: for if they ſhould ſuffer the fire of grace to bee quenched by the impure ſtreames of ſinne and iniquitie, Gods ſpirit ſhould be put to the worſt, which is no leſſe then blaſphemie for any one to imagine that it ſhould euer come to paſſe: for it doth work faith in mens harts, which is indefatiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and inuincible: which in time of temptation, will ſue vnto heauen, and ſearch the word, and vſe all lawfull
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19247:19"/> meanes &amp; helpes for the procuring of ſtrength againſt ſinne: ſo that though there be many enemies againſt it, yet will it not be ſet downe by any of them; &amp; though it doe now and then receiue a wound, yet will it recouer againe, and carrie away the victorie in the end.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Vſe. 1.</note> Hereby then (to drawe to ſome vſe of this doctrine) we may make ſome triall of the ſtrength or weakeneſſe of our faith; according as we are more or leſſe able to ſee the ſinfulnes of our nature, and to ſtriue againſt it: ſo are we to iudge of the meaſure of Gods grace in vs, to be more or leſſe: and if we do not particularly diſcerne of the corruptions of the fleſh, or do not loathe them, and labour to be cured of them, but rather excuſe and exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate them, and hide and cheriſh them, this is an infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible ſigne, that we haue in vs no ſauing grace at all. Let all ſuch therefore as would haue the teſtimonie of Gods children, vſe their beſt endeuour to haue their eyes ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that they may perceiue the ſeuerall euils that lurke within their hearts; and let them withall get ſuch an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation againſt them, that they may (as this man did) come vnto Chriſt Ieſus to be cured of them: which if they can doe, their very approaching vnto him by prayer, and in the vſe of this ordinances, will cauſe them euery day to become more ſharpe-ſighted than other, ſo that they ſhall (with the holy prophet <hi>Iſaiah. Chap.</hi> 6.) cry out againſt their pollutions, and ſo get pardon of them, and power ouer them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">2</note> Secondly, this makes for the confutation of ſuch, as being vrged to reforme themſelues, are readie to ſay, that all things are ſo well with them, that they neede no amendment; they know not where to beginne their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe they ſee nothing amiſſe: Theſe kinde of men are moſt buſie againſt others, that complaine of their owne wants, and ſeeke to haue them ſupplied from heauen; and ſuch they account and call Puritans, who
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19247:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> indeed do moſt ſee and acknowledge and bewaile their owne puritie: but in truth they the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues do ſarre better deſerue that name, for that they imagine they haue at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained ſuch a meaſure of puritie, as that nothing can be added thereunto: they haue knowledge enough, faith enough, and repentance enough, and therefore they profeſſe that they care not for preaching, and that they had rather be without it, then be troubled with it. Of ſuch the wiſe man ſpeaketh thus, <note place="margin">Prou. 30. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>There is a generation that is pure in their owne conceit, and yet are not waſhed from their filthineſſe:</hi> the world doth euen ſwarme with ſuch vngracious perſons, vpon whom the Sonne of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes did neuer yet ſhine, and therefore they are vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly blinde that they cannot ſee, or wilfull, that they will not reforme their euill and corrupt waies and workes: which is a ſure and certaine note of groſſe infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and of an vtter want of all grace and goodnes in them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Vſe. 3.</note> Thirdly, from this point doth ariſe an vſe of ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar conſolation vnto Gods ſeruants, that are troubled with the ſight and ſenſe of their corruptions, that doe finde pride working in them, and vnbeliefe ſtirring in their hearts, and many vncharitable thoughts and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſtill remaining in their ſoules: all the while they apprehend the vileneſſe and hurtfulneſſe of them, and withall mourne for them, and confeſſe them, and ſeeke vnto the Lord for pardon of them, and power againſt them, they neede not be diſcouraged; nay they haue iuſt cauſe to be comforted herein: as knowing that it is a certaine marke, and vndoubted note of grace to be thus affected. They may be aſſured, that ſo long as they feele their ſickneſſe, they are not dead; eſpecially if withall they be hungrie &amp; thirſtie after ſpirituall things, and finde an appetite vnto the foode of life, and with much paines and diligence ſeeke for the ſame; there is
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19247:20"/> then no reaſon in the world that they ſhould make queſtion of the goodneſſe of their eſtate, as hauing in them the ſpeciall ſignes of true conuerſion, and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="sermon">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:19247:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>The third Sermon.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>VERSE. 25.</bibl>
                     <p>When IESVS ſaw that the people came together, hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buked the vncleane ſpirit, ſaying vnto him; Thou dumbe and deafe ſpirit, I charge thee come out of him, and enter no more into him.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>26.</bibl> Then the ſpirit cryed, and rent him ſore, and came out, and hee was as one dead; in ſo much that many ſaid, hee is dead.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the former part of this ſtorie, is ſet downe the earneſt ſuite of the man whoſe childe was poſſeſſed, for the eaſing and relieuing of his diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſonne. In theſe words is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red how our Sauior performed that which he required, <hi>viz.</hi> that he caſt the diuell out of his childe: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we may note two things, to wit
<list>
                     <item>the occaſion of it:</item>
                     <item>the manner of it.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, for the occaſion thereof, it was two-fold, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. the good, and holie, and gracious profeſſion of the man, ſpoken of before; <hi>Lord, I beleeue, helpe mine vnbeleefe.</hi> Chriſt had tolde him, that if he could beleeue, all things were poſſible to the beleeuer: and for that hee truely
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19247:21"/> auoucheth that hee did in part beleeue, and whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> his faith was weake, hee deſires to haue it ſtrengthened<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and giues Chriſt Ieſus that honour, as to pray vnto hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> to ſtrengthen it. This our Sauiour approueth of, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>is was one occaſion of the miracle. 2. An other was the concourſe of the people, verſ. 25. <hi>When Ieſus ſaw that the people came running together, hee rebuked the vncleane ſpirit, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Diſciples (as we haue heard before) were not able to caſt out this diuell. Herevpon, the multitude ſeeing the man to deale with Chriſt himſelfe about the ſame matter, they flocked together, to ſee what would come of it. Some of them (no doubt) with a good minde, that if a miracle were wrought in their ſight, they might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce at it, and haue their faith confirmed by it. Other ſome, to the ende that they might inſult ouer our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt, if the miracle had beene either not wrought at all, or but onely protracted for a time; He therefore to preuent diſcouragment in the better ſort, and inſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in the reſt, preſentlie ſetteth vpon the worke. Thus much for the occaſion. The manner followeth, where wee may obſerue, 1. what Chriſt ſpake vnto the diuell. 2. what the diuell did vnto the childe.</p>
               <p>For the former, it is ſaid, that hee 1. <hi>rebuked the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane ſpirit:</hi> and 2. diſcharged him of the place where he was, commaunding him to <hi>come forth, and to returne no more,</hi> verſ. 25.</p>
               <p>Concerning the diuels dealing with the childe, it is ſaide, 1. that hee did <hi>rent</hi> and teare him grieuouſlie, (being vexed and tormented, becauſe he muſt leaue his former hold) in ſo much, that manie thought the child had beene dead: 2. <hi>hee came out of him,</hi> euen as Chriſt had charged him. And thus much for the order and meaning of the Text.</p>
               <p>Verſ. 25. <hi>When Ieſus ſaw that the people came running
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19247:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> together, hee rebuked the vncleane ſpirit.</hi>]</p>
               <p>Now hee ſaw there was a fitte opportunitie, becauſe there would bee moſt vſe of it: if hee had done it ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, the people would not ſo well haue perceiued and marked it, with all the circumſtances thereof: if he had deferred it longer, ſome of them would haue departed, (it may bee) others would haue beene diſmayed: and a third ſort would haue gloried and triumphed; as if now he that had done ſo many miracles, had bene at a ſtand, and mette with an vncleane ſpirite, that was too ſtrong for him, and would not go out at his bidding. Now in that Chriſt doth take this occaſion of doing this mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous worke, the Doctrine is, <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> 1. Chriſt doth all ſeaſonablie.</note> that Chriſt doeth all his workes in the fitteſt ſeaſon.</p>
               <p>This Doctrine is euident in ſundry places of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel after <hi>Iohn,</hi> as chapt. 2. when the Mother of Chriſt would haue him to turne water into wine at her ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment: hee anſwereth, <note place="margin">Iohn. 2. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>mine houre is not yet come:</hi> though in all probabilitie, hee wrought that miracle within the ſpace of an houre after: yet hee ſaith, <hi>mine houre is not yet come:</hi> meaning the very inſtant where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in that worke was to bee done. Which giueth vs to vnderſtand, that hee will not faile an haires breadth of the very moment wherein euery good thing ſhould be done. Againe, <hi>Iohn</hi> 7. when his brethren would haue had him haſten to the feaſt of <hi>Tabernacle</hi> at <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> hee ſaith, <note place="margin">Iohn. 7. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>I will not goe vp yet, for my time is not yet fulfilled.</hi> And likewiſe in the 11. chapt. of that Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, after that hee knew <hi>Lazarus</hi> was dead, hee made no great haſt vnto him, but ſtayed till hee had beene dead foure daies: telling his Diſciples, <note place="margin">Iohn. 71. 15.</note> that <hi>hee was glad that he was not there no ſooner:</hi> whereas <hi>Lazarus</hi> ſiſters, <hi>Marie</hi> and <hi>Martha,</hi> were euen diſcouraged at his long ſtay. But hee in his wiſedome choſe that time aboue anie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe if hee had raiſed <hi>Lazarus</hi> being newly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19247:22"/> it had not beene ſo admirable, it being now a common caſe, and a thing that Chriſt had done for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: but when he had beene dead foure daies, and was laide in his graue, ſo that <hi>Martha</hi> was vnwilling that Chriſt ſhould meddle with him: now to reſtore him from death to life, was a thing very remarkeable; and therefore tooke he this ſeaſon for the effecting of this miracle. <note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſon.</note> Now the reaſon of this point is,</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">1</note> Firſt, becauſe he reſpecteth his owne glorie and his peoples good: therefore is he willing to finde out the fitteſt time for euery buſines.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">2</note> Secondly, as that is the end which he propoſeth, ſo is he full of all heauenly wiſedome, &amp; therefore knowes the very preciſe time, when euery worke ought to be done; yea he doth predeſtinate the ſeaſons wherein all things ſhall be accompliſhed: men oftentimes meete with an opportunitie at vnawares, and therefore it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt paſt before they can take hold of it, but God hath eternally fore-appointed it; in which regard, he doth all things in the fulnes of time: euen when that time is come which he had preordained in his ſecret counſell.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">3</note> Thirdly, he is of power and abilitie to do euery thing in the fit ſeaſon thereof. Men are driuen to deferre mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, albeit they ſee opportunitie for the doing of them, becauſe their ſtrength will not then ſerue them to goe thorough with that which they deſire: but the Lord is of all ſufficiencie, for the performance of whatſoeuer pleaſeth him; ſo that he needs not make delaies when the time ſerueth him.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Vſe. 1.</note> Is it ſo then (as it hath beene plainely prooued) that Chriſt doth euery thing in due time? Let vs he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce learne to imitate our Sauiour, that we may be able to yeeld a good and ſound reaſon why we do this or that now, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than at any other time. For that which <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith of words, that a <hi>word ſpoken in due ſeaſon, is like apples
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19247:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> of golde, with pictures of ſiluer</hi> (that is verie beautifull;) holdes as true of actions, whoſe grace it is to be done in that time which is beſt befitting them. There are times for the exerciſes of religion, and there are times for the works of our vocation, and both muſt be rightly diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and wiſely followed. There are times to mourne and to be ſorrowfull: and it is a great faulte for men to reioyce, <note place="margin">Iſa. 22.</note> when the Lord calleth them to heauineſſe, and to teares. Againe, there are times to be merry and glad, (in a good and holie manner,) and it is an offence for Chriſtians, not to bee cheerfull with thoſe that they conuerſe with, when God giueth them occaſion of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">2</note> Secondly, let this teach vs to commit and ſubmit our ſelues, our eſtate, and all that we haue, to Gods wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: neither let vs murmure, nor grow diſcontented at the delayes that hee makes, but waite his leiſure, and be content that he ſhould take his owne time; aſſuring our ſelues, that hee will not faile one moment, when we are ready for any bleſſing and benefite: but the longer he deferres, the more it ſhall tende to his owne glorie and our good. Manie would haue their harueſt before it be ripe, but God is wiſer then they are, and therefore hee cauſeth them to ſpend many prayers and teares, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they obtaine their hearts deſire. If Gods owne chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren might haue deliuerance for themſelues, or for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſo ſoone as they deſire, it would prooue to bee as an vntimely birth, which is euen dead before it come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world: and therefore the Lord putteth them off from time to time, that their comfort in the ende might be more full and complete. In which regard, we ſhould with patience depend vpon him, till ſuch time as hee pleaſe to haue mercie vpon vs: <note place="margin" type="runSum">How we may bee able to waite on God. 1</note> which that wee may be able to doe, obſerue me this direction following.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">1</note> Firſt, let let vs doe our beſt endeuour to repreſſe car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19247:23"/> reaſon: for otherwiſe that time which ſeemeth beſt vnto God, will oftentimes ſeeme worſt vnto vs.</p>
               <p>When hee thinkes it too ſoone for vs to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſuch and ſuch bleſſings, we ſhall thinke it high time that we had them: and when he iudgeth it a fit ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for vs, or any of his people to be deliuered, we ſhall imagine it to be too late. <hi>Zacharie</hi> yeelding to his car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall reaſon, <note place="margin">Luke. 1.</note> thought that God had paſt his time for gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing him a ſonne, and therfore though an Angell from heauen brought him that meſſage, he would not giue credit vnto it: if he had heard ſuch tidings twentie yeares before, he would haue thought there had beene ſome likelihood in the matter: ſo in other caſes, how dangerous a thing would it haue beene to conſult with fleſh and bloud concerning the time of accompliſhing things? who would haue iudged it wiſedome in God to ſuffer his people ſo farre to be endangered in <hi>Egipt,</hi> and after to be condemned by the <hi>Perſian</hi> king? <note place="margin">Exod. 3. Heſter. 3. &amp; 4. 7.</note> to ſuffer <hi>Peter</hi> to be ſo ſtraitly impriſoned, <hi>Daniel</hi> to be caſt into the lions denne, and the three children into the firie fornace? if a man ſhould haue conſulted with his owne wiſedome, he would haue thought the Lord too ſlacke in freeing his ſeruants, and that their caſes were euen deſperate and quite paſt recouerie: yet he did but ſtay the fitteſt time for their deliuerance: which being once come, the Lord ſet them at libertie, notwithſtanding all the difficulties and extremities wherein they were.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">2</note> Secondly, let vs labour for faith, by vertue whereof we may repreſſe all our fleſhly affections, which will be readie to oppoſe themſelues againſt the Lords wiſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings; as may be ſeene in <hi>Iacob,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 37. 34. 35.</note> whoſe affection of griefe was immoderately ſtirred, when he imagined that his ſonne <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was deuoured by ſome wilde beaſt: how much more (thinke we) would it haue troubled him, if he had knowne how his ſonnes had dealt with him, and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19247:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> how <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was dealt with in the land of <hi>Egipt,</hi> when <note place="margin">Pſal. 106. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>his feete were held faſt in the ſtocks, and he was laid in yrons?</hi> yet all this was for his good, and for the benefite of <hi>Iacob</hi> and all his houſhold, that he ſhould be thus afflicted vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till his appointed time came, when the Lord would haue him deliuered and aduanced: therfore let vs curbe and reſtraine our boiſterous affections, labouring euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more to bring them into ſubiection vnto Gods moſt ſacred and bleſſed will, and reſoluing that his time is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies the beſt time for euery thing that falleth out vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Sunne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He rebuked the vncleane ſpirit</hi>] Hence we may note this doctrine, that</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> 2. Enemies of Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſhalbe rebuked.</note> The greateſt and moſt mightie oppreſſors of Gods children, ſhalbe rebuked by Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
               <p>Sathan in this childe kept his holde, and did deride whatſoeuer power of men came againſt him: yea if all the forces in the world had attempted to caſt him out, he would haue kept poſſeſſion in deſpite of them all: yet our Sauiour ſets on him, and rebukes him, and that effectually. So that let thoſe tyrants that vexe and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt Gods people be neuer ſo mightie, they ſhall heare of their wretched dealings, and that to the torment of their hearts: as it fared with the diuell in this place, who knowes how many commanders he had commanded (being a worldly gouernour, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. 22.) and how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny rulers he had ruled: yet now (we ſee) he is control<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and reſtrained by our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. Thus hath the Lord dealt heretofore with the enemies of his Church, as it is ſaid of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 105. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>He ſuffered no man to doe them wrong, but reproued kings for their ſakes.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to this point is the prophecie of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> who ſpeaketh thus concerning Chriſt, <note place="margin">Iſaiah. 11. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>With righteouſnes ſhall he iudge the Poore, and with equitie ſhall he reproue for the meeke of the earth:</hi> that is, for ſuch as are lowe and meane,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19247:24"/> and ſuch as will not returne rebuke for rebuke, neither are of abilitie to withſtand their aduerſaries, their quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell will hee take in hand: and though the whole earth ſhould ioyne together againſt them, yet will hee ſmite them, and either rebuke their hearts gratiouſlie vnto their conuerſion, or elſe ſtrike them in wrath and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure to their vtter confuſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſon.</note> The reaſon why oppreſſours ſhall bee thus dealt with, is,</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">1.</note> Firſt, becauſe they oppoſe themſelues againſt Chriſt himſelfe: <hi>Hee that oppreſſeth the poore</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon,</hi>) <note place="margin">Prou, 14. 31.</note> 
                  <hi>reproueth him that made him:</hi> euen him that is the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the fatherleſſe, and the protector of ſuch as are poore and needy: and therefore becauſe his gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is contemned, it is equall that hee ſhould reproue ſuch offenders.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">2</note> Secondly, he hath as great authoritie ouer the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt as ouer the meaneſt; ouer the higheſt Prince, as ouer the baſeſt vaſſall: and therefore hee that in equitie may and will proceed againſt the meaneſt, may and will alſo doe the like againſt the mightieſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">3</note> Thirdly, as hee hath authoritie, ſo is he alſo furniſhed with ability: ſo that he wil not only vſe words of rebuke as many times men doe: but they who are rebuked by him, ſhall feele that his reproofes do pierce their ſoules, as the diuell himſelfe did in this place: they ſhall finde that his wordes are not as weake reedes, but as ſharpe darts, that will enter deepe, and tarry long, euen till ſuch time as it pleaſeth him to plucke them foorth of their woundes. Therefore it is that the Prophet ſaith, <note place="margin">Pſal. 76. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>At thy rebuke ô God of Iacob, both the Charret and horſe are fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len a ſleepe. The ſtout-harted are ſpoyled, they haue ſlept their ſleepe, and all the men of ſtrength haue not found their hands.</hi> Where wee ſee what force the Lords voice doth carrie with it: for it makes the principall men of warre, and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19247:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> the moſt valiant Captaines to tremble and quake, and to be vtterly daunted, and diſmayed: <hi>yea, if hee doe but rebuke the mountaines, they ſhall ſmoake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Vſe. 1.</note> This Doctrine ſerueth firſt of all, for admonition vnto thoſe that haue power and might in their handes, that they doe not vſe the ſame to wring and pinch the Seruants of God; nor to grinde the faces of the poore. For if they once abuſe their places, they forfeit them vnto the Lord, who will call them to a ſtrickt recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, for peruerting iuſtice, &amp; iudgement, and for vſing that authority which he hath beſtowed vpon them, to a wrong ende and purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Therefore let all ſuch as haue anie ſuperioritie, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in publike or in priuate, carie themſelues humblie, and Chriſtianlie; not contemning any one, leſt they be contemned of the Lord: nor wronging the meaneſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their charge, leaſt they bee cenſured by him that iudgeth all men indifferentlie; without anie reſpect of perſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">2</note> Secondly, here is another vſe of inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that ſeeing the Lord will checke &amp; controll the moſt violent &amp; fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious enemies of his children, therefore when we are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iured and oppreſſed by ſuch manner of men, we ſhould containe our ſelues within the compaſſe of patience, and modeſtie, committing and commending our ſelues and our cauſes vnto God, who will in due time right vs, and plague our enemies. Whereas if wee growe as boyſterous and iniurious as our aduerſaries, and goe about to render vnto them like for like, wee ſhall looſe our peace with God; we ſhall draw his afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting hand vpon vs; and ſhall more exaſperate and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitter the affections of men againſt vs.</p>
               <p>Let vs therefore commend our ſelues, and all our matters, vnto him that iudgeth righteouſlie: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as <hi>Dauid</hi> did, Pſalme 38. verſ. 12. 13.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:19247:25"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>They that ſeeke after my life</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>lay ſnares, and they that goe about to doe me euill, talke wicked things, and imagine deceit continually.</hi> But what did he in this cafe? <hi>I as a deafe man heard not, and am as a dumbe man which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth not his mouth.</hi> When he was railed vpon and abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, yea when he was purſued for his life, he was as if he had not heard the matter, euen as if he had beene deafe, or if he were ſenſible of ſome things, yet he was as a dumbe man, and opened not his mouth in any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachfull or reuengefull manner: and what was the reaſon hereof? he himſelfe telleth vs, <hi>verſe.</hi> 15. <hi>On thee ô Lord doe I waite; thou wilt heare me, my Lord, my God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, who is greater than all, when he was wronged by the diuell himſelfe, <hi>durſt not</hi> (as <hi>Iude</hi> ſaith) <hi>blame him with curſed ſpeaking:</hi> but ſaid, <hi>the Lord rebuked thee.</hi> Though Chriſt were the beſt that was, yet would not he vſe rayling tearmes againſt Sathan, the worſt that was: for if he had, he had nothing hurt the diuell thereby: and therefore he tooke a better courſe, deliuering him ouer vnto Gods hands, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring him to rebuke him; which was the moſt terrible thing that could haue beene done againſt Sathan. Theſe examples let vs imitate when we haue to deale with wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked perſons, neuer vſe any reuiling words againſt them, but referre the matter vnto the Lord, beſeeching him to paſſe a righteous ſentence: not abſolutely deſiring to haue them puniſhed, as our Sauiour did, and we may concerning Sathan, but rather wiſhing that they may be ſo rebuked in this world, as that they may eſcape that eternall rebuke, which the diuell cannot auoide.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou dumbe and deafe ſpirit, I charge thee, &amp;c.</hi>] Here we muſt vnderſtand, that when our Sauiour calleth the diuell <hi>dumbe and deafe ſpirit,</hi> the meaning is not that ſome diuels can ſpeake and heare, and others not; but he is thus tearmed, in regard of the effects which he
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19247:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> wrought in this child, in making him dumbe and deafe. Which (as it ſeemes) was his manner of dealing, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer hee tooke poſſeſſion of anie. Where wee may obſerue what is the nature of Sathan: for all the diuels are of the ſame diſpoſition, if it lie in their power, from which, let vs note this Doctrine; that,</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> 3. Sathan is deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaue vs of our ſenſes and limbes.</note> If the Lord did not reſtraine Sathan, hee would (in his malice) depriue vs of our ſenſes, &amp; of the vſe of our naturall parts. Such is his quarrell againſt mankinde, and ſuch is that naturall force which is giuen vnto him, that if hee were not curbed by a diuine hand, he would not only bereaue vs of eternall ſaluation, but alſo take from vs the vſe of our eies, and of our eares, and of our other ſenſes and limbes.</p>
               <p>In this regard, it is ſaid in other places of Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, <note place="margin">Matth. 12. 22. Luke. 11. 14.</note> that he <hi>caſt out a diuell of one that was blinde &amp; dumbe;</hi> to ſhewe what worke Sathan makes, where hee hath li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie to doe according to his will in ſuch particulars. <note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſons.</note> And the reaſons mouing him thus to deale; are theſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">1</note> Firſt, that enmitie that hee carries not onely towards the ſoules, but alſo towards the bodies of men, ſtirreth him vp herevnto: his quarrell towards vs is ſo great, that hee would not onely ſhut vs out of heauen, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude vs from all ſpirituall comforts, but alſo make vs miſerable vpon the face of the earth; and for that ende, ſtrike vs with blindeneſſe, or lameneſſe, or deafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or the like; that our life might bee vtterly voyd of all manner of pleaſures, and contentments. This reſon was touched in one of the former doctrines.<note place="margin">See Serm. 1. Doct. 1.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">2</note> Secondly, his malice againſt God is ſuch, that hee would not haue him to haue any ſeruice from men: he malignes that they ſhould haue eyes to ſee any thing, or eares to heare any thing, whereby they might be ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp to yeelde praiſes and obedience vnto the Lord, and therfore his deſire is to depriue them of thoſe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:19247:26"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">3</note> Laſtly, he knoweth that theſe naturall powers and faculties are very neceſſarie helpes to further men vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to eternall life: <note place="margin">Rom. 10. Pſal. 19.</note> he is not ignorant that <hi>faith comes by hearing,</hi> and that knowledge and holineſſe is much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed by ſeeing and obſeruing the workes of God, and ſome of the ordinances of God; and therefore carrying a deadly hatred againſt the ſaluation of men, he ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uors to take from them all thoſe naturall inſtruments, whereby they might be furthered vnto euerlaſting happineſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Vſe. 1.</note> The conſideration whereof ſhould in the firſt place ſtirre vs vp to continuall thankfulneſſe: for were not the Lords mercifull and prouident hand ſtill ſtretched out for our protection and defence, Sathan would make vs fearefull ſpectacles of much woe and miſerie, and cauſe vs to ſpend all our daies in heauines and penſiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in regard of the euils by him inflicted on vs. We ſhould not haue an eye to looke vpon the glorious frame and fabricke of the heauens and the earth; nor vpon the beautie and excellencie of any of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: we ſhould not (might the diuell haue his will) enioy our eares, to heare the voyce of the Lord ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding forth comfort vnto vs: neither ſhould we haue the vſe of our taſte, to refreſh our ſelues with any of the good and ſweete creatures of God appointed for that end, he would cauſe our tongues to cleaue vnto the roofe of our mouthes, ſo that we ſhould not be able to vtter forth the praiſes of the Lord, nor to ſpeake of his wonderfull workes, or of his holy word before the ſons of men: In a word, there is none of the parts of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, which is now vſefull and comfortable vnto vs, but he would much afflict vs therein, and vtterly depriue vs of all benefite thereof, which ſhould cauſe vs to be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thankfull for our ſenſes and members, while we doe enioy them, and wholy to conſecrate them vnto the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19247:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> Lord, who vouchaſeth vs the comfortable vſe of them, and no way to abuſe them in the ſeruice of Sathan, leaſt God in his iuſtice grant him libertie altogether to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaue vs of any of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Vſe. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Secondly, ſith the diuell is euermore readie to doe vs a miſchiefe, let this teach vs alwaies to keepe in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour with God; for otherwiſe wee ſee in what perill wee ſtand; if he doe but turne Sathan looſe vpon vs, he will quickly make vs blinde, or lame, or dumbe, or deafe, or ſtrike vs in ſome grieuous &amp; fearefull manner or other: he watcheth his oportunitie, and if he ſee an aduantage, he will ſuddenly be vpon vs, ere we be aware: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs aboue all things be careful to keep our peace with God, who is our keeper and preſeruer, that <note place="margin">Pſal. 91.</note> 
                  <hi>deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vs from the ſnare of the hunter, that couereth vs vnder his wings, and keepeth vs ſafe vnder his feathers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">3</note> Thirdly, is it ſo, that Sathan is maruellous malicious againſt our bodies? then let vs looke heedfully to our ſoules, for he carrieth farre greater ſpite againſt them: and then he is in his proper element, when he deales a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our inward man, hee laboureth to depriue vs of our natural powers, of hearing, &amp; ſeeing, &amp; ſpeaking, &amp;c: But eſpecially he ſeeketh to keepe vs from hearing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſly, from ſeeing ſpiritually, and from ſpeaking profitably: the former priuation of the naturall facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties befalleth but a fewe: but this latter ouertaketh all the vnregenerate men of the world, and the regenerate alſo in a great part; all men are very deafe, where they ſhould heare, and blinde in things that they ſhould ſee; and haue their mouthes ſhut vp, where they are required principally to ſpeake: In which regard, the prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaking of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſion of men, ſaith; <hi>Then ſhall the eyes of the blinde be lightened, and the eares of the deafe be opened.</hi> Which is to be vnderſtood ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, not litterally: the meditation of which point,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19247:27"/> 
                  <hi>viz:</hi> that Sathan doth ſo mightily preuaile againſt the ſoules of the multitude, ſhould make vs very warie, leaſt he circumuent vs; and cauſe vs continually to cry vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord for grace and fauour, and for ſtrength and aſſiſtance, that the diuell may not blinde the eyes of our minde, nor ſhut vp our eares from liſtening vnto holy things, nor cauſe vs to be as it were tongue-tyed, when we ſhould ſpeake of ſuch things as make for his glorie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I charge thee come out of him.</hi>] From which words, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with that which followeth, to witte, that <hi>the ſpirit came out,</hi> this doctrine ariſeth, that,</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> 4. A word of Chriſts mouth is ſufficient to helpe vs out of all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes.</note> A word of the mouth of Chriſt is ſufficient to helpe againſt any miſeries, and to ſet vs free from any ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
               <p>This good man and his childe were both ſorely di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed by reaſon of this vncleane ſpirit: yet when our Sauiour doth but ſpeake the word, their enemie is van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed and expelled; their miſerie accompliſhed and ended.</p>
               <p>This power doth the leaper in the <hi>Goſpell</hi> aſcribe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, <hi>Maiſter, if thou wilt</hi> (ſaith he) <note place="margin">Math. 8. 2. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>thou canſt make me cleane;</hi> and ſo it came to paſſe: for <hi>he putting forth his hand, and touching him, ſaying, I will, be thou cleane: his le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie was immediately clenſed.</hi> And the like doth the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turion; <note place="margin">Verſe. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord ſpeake the word onely, and my ſeruant ſhalbe healed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in the Goſpell according to the Euangeliſt <hi>Marke,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Marke. 5. 9.</note> we reade how our Sauiour with his onely word, did preſently caſt forth an whole armie of diuells: ſo that though there be ten thouſand of them vniting their forces together, he is as able to expell them all, as if there were but one alone. And as it is in theſe caſes that haue beene named, ſo it is in all other diſtreſſes whatſoeuer: the very becke of God is ſufficient to free
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:19247:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> vs from them all, as is at large ſhewed in the hundreth and ſeuenth Pſalme.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſons.</note> The reaſons of this point are two.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">1</note> Firſt, by the word of the Lord were all the creatures made; <note place="margin">Pſalm. 33.</note> euen the good Angells, and thoſe that are now euill Angells: If then Gods power were ſuch in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king all Creatures, it is euery whit as great for the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering of his ſeruants.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <note place="margin">Heb. 1. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>All things are ſupported by the Word of his power.</hi> Now if all the Creatures haue their preſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from him, what difficultie is it for him to deliuer ſome fewe of them?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Vſe 1.</note> Here then is matter of great comfort for all ſuch as doe vnfainedly and from their hearts feare the Lorde; for they haue the word of Chriſt for them, which can eaſily either preſerue them from miſerie, or ridde them of it, if it fall vpon them. If a good earthly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could by his word alone preſerue his Children from perill, from the priſon, from death it ſelfe, would hee bee ſilent and dumbe, and not open his mouth in their behalfe? None can imagine that a father can be ſo deuoide of naturall affection: and ſhall wee thinke that the Lord is leſſe pittifull then men? doeth hee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid crueltie in them, and ſhall wee conceiue that it may be found in himſelfe? Bee it farre from vs: nay, though there bee neuer ſo many aduerſaries that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine themſelues, and neuer ſo manie miſchiefes bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended againſt vs: albeit the world be full of cloudes, and of ſtormes, and all things ſeeme to threaten an vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ouerthrow vnto vs, yet let vs ſatiſfie and pacifie our hearts with this, that one word of Chriſt is ſufficient to helpe vs out of all dangers and difficulties. And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, let vs aſſure our ſelues, that the Lord will ſpeake, and that effectually in due time, ſo that all the outrage and furie of men ſhall bee ſuppreſſed, and all troubles
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19247:28"/> and calamities that lye vpon vs ſhall be ſuddenly diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. God needes not any long time for the effecting of it: As wee ſee in <hi>Eſters</hi> dayes, when all the Church of God ſeemed ouernight to be the moſt miſerable peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the world; and yet the next day they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed (and ſo were eſteemed) the happieſt people vnder the Sunne; So that well was hee then that might bee a <hi>Iewe.</hi> Let this therefore bee our conſolation, that though our ruines and decayes be neuer ſo many, and great, and grieuous, yet if God doe but ſay the word, all ſhall be repaired and recouered.</p>
               <p>And as it is for outward miſeries, ſo doth it hold as ſtrongly for ſpirituall diſtreſſes, and for the enemies of our ſoules, that if our Lord and Sauiour doe but vtter his voice againſt them, we ſhall quickly preuaile ouer them: though Sathan haue a deadly quarrell againſt vs, and our owne pride and couetouſneſſe, and wrath, be farre too ſtrong for vs, yet if the Lord pleaſe to worke in vs by the mightie word of his grace, wee ſhall eaſily tread theſe ſpirituall enemies of ours vnder our feete, and get the victorie ouer them all. Yea though we were vtter aduerſaries vnto God, as <hi>Paul,</hi> and the <hi>Gayler</hi> were, yet if he doe but ſpeake vnto our conſciences from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, wee ſhall ſpeedily alter our courſes, and become faithfull and ſeruiceable vnto his maieſtie.</p>
               <p>Secondly, heere is matter of terror for all impious and irreligious perſons: for if the word of God be ſo mightie for the ſuccour of his children, it is euery whit as powerfull for the ouerthrow of his aduerſaries: and doe they thinke that they ſhalbe able to ſtand when the Lord of hoaſtes commeth againſt them? doe blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, and Sabbath-breakers, and raylers, and filthy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, imagine that they ſhall ſtill carrie out matters as they haue done, when their Creator comes to plague
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19247:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> and puniſh them? if they doe, they greatly deceiue themſelues, for he needeth not to muſter an armie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them: but his very will and purpoſe is ſufficient to procure their confuſion and vtter deſtruction.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Come out of him, and enter no more into him.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>Whence note this doctrine, that, It is all one with Chriſt to driue the diuell out, and to keepe him out, he can doe the latter, as well as the former.</p>
               <q>Verſe. 26. <hi>Then the ſpirit [cried,] and [rent him ſore.]</hi>
               </q>
               <p>Whence obſerue, that, Sathan neuer ſeemes more maſterfull, than when hee is ouer-maſtered.<note place="margin">Theſe. 2. points were no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for want of time.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:19247:29"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19247:29"/>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by Th. C. for <hi>VVilliam VVelbie,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yarde, at the ſigne of the Swanne. 1611.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
